Guide to the Records of the New York University College of Dentistry RG.25
New York University Archives
Records of the New York University College of Dentistry
1550-2003
1850-1950
New York University Archives
New York University. College of Dentistry
RG.25
65 Linear Feet in 61 boxes
The New York College of Dentistry was founded in 1865 with 31 students and ten faculty members. In 1925, the College merged with New York University (NYU) and developed into a leading center for dental care, research and policy. This collection allows the viewer to understand the school's development through a series of student notebooks and administrative files from the late 1800s and early 1900s. It also contains a wide array of antique dental tools and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Some materials in this collection are extremely fragile and require preservation treatment before being made accessible to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the University Archives by the Waldman Library of the New York University College of Dentistry in August 2000; additional materials were transferred in December of 2015. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 80-011, 94-021, 03-006, 2016-002. An accretion was added in 2022.
Arrangement
General administrative documents are filed chronologically by subject. Student materials are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the student. Accreditation materials are in their original order.
The files are grouped into four series:
Series I: General Administration
Series II: Memorabilia
Series III: Student Records
Series IV: Accreditation Records
Historical Note
The New York College of Dentistry was established in 1865 in a small rental space on 22nd Street and Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. The mission of the College was to promote altruism in dentistry while providing first-rate education. Upon its inception, the school had 31 students and 10 faculty members. Only 9 of the original 31 students graduated in the first graduating class.
When the New York College of Dentistry merged with New York University in 1925, it became known as the New York University College of Dentistry. The merger led to the creation of a dental school at the forefront of research and postdoctoral education.
Today, the College of Dentistry has approximately 1,600 students from across the world. About fifty percent of the student body is female, and fifty percent are minority students. The greater aim of the College is to improve the health of underserved populations, and more generally, to improve health worldwide.
The New York University College of Dentistry offers D.D.S., B.S. and A.A.S. degrees. It is now the third oldest and the largest private dental school in the United States.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes administrative and student records, memorabilia, and a large collection of dental tools and models.
Separated Materials
Promotional materials, bulletins, annual reports, publications, commencement records, audiovisual materials, and photographs were incorporated into the general University Archives collections for those formats.
Dentistry -- Study and teaching; Dental instruments and apparatus.
- Series I: Administrative Records, 1851-1996; 7 Linear Feet in 13 manuscript boxes, one flat box, and one custom box.
  - Accreditation, Kriser Dental Center Waldmann Dental Library, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Act of Incorporation of NYCD, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agreement between NYU and NYCD, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book of Contacts, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Centennial Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centennial History, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clinical Fee Schedules, 1977, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clinic book, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clinics, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dean's Memoranda, 1960-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dean Edward G. Kaufman Memoranda, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department of Preventive Dentistry and Community Health, Dental Health Organizations, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Educational Standards, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faculty Committee on the Role and Function of the Faculty, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bethune Stein Physiology Lectures, 1900-1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty, Minutes, 1869-1895 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty, Meeting Minutes, 1898-1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty, Progress Examinations, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Faculty Records, Graduates, 1915-1923 (Box 4)
  - Faculty Records, Graduates, 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Guest Book, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Henry Dodge Record of Operations, 1868 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Henry Dodge Day Book, 1851-1852 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1934-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Gifts/Donations, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Investigation into Theft, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Murray and Leone Guggenheim Foundation for Dental Research, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Parent Agreement for Minors, 1920-1921 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Peridontia Corresponding Group, Bulletin 1- 25, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Undergraduate Preventative Dentistry Variety Show, 1968-1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Registration, Applications, 1919-1924 (Box 7)
  - Registration, Applications, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Report on Oral Surgery Clinic, 1890-1893 (Box 9, Folder 2-5)
  - Student Records: Expelled students, non-attending students, qualifying certificates, signature book, Student Council, certificate, NYU Journal of Dentistry article, 1897-1966 (Box 10)
  - Student record book, non-attending students, 1866-1910 (Box 11)
  - Qualifying Students, 1918-1925 (Box 12, Box 13)
  - Trustees and Directors, 1865-1914 (Box 13, Box 15)
  - Faculty Group Portrait, 1917 (Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Group Portrait, 1909 (Folder 3)
  - Mural on the History of Anesthesia, 1938 (Folder 4)
  - Faculty Group Portrait, 1923 (Folder 5)
  - Portrait, circa 1920s (Box Shared University Archives 052, Folder 5)
  - Portrait, circa 1930s-1950s (Box Shared University Archives 008, Folder 8)
- Series II: Memorabilia
  - Medallions (10), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Paperweights (3), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 19th Century Dental Tools (100+), 1800-1900
  - Model teeth, undated
  - Small Metal Tools (10), undated
  - Moldings (2), undated
  - Model Teeth (8), undated
  - Model Teeth, undated
  - Tools (20), undated
  - Film Reel, undated (Box 43)
  - Dental tool, undated
    Provenance
    This item was given to Dr. Waldman by John Steinbeck.
  - Metal Plates (2), undated
  - Plaques (6), undated
  - Post Extractor, undated
  - Film, undated (Box 43)
  - Condyles (27), undated
  - Pins (6), undated
  - Gysi Trubyte Articulator, undated
  - Tools (28), undated
  - Shells (5), undated
  - Facebow, undated
  - Antique Instruments (25), undated
    These items were a gift from Erum Kaplan.
  - Stamps, undated
  - Atomizer, undated
  - Model Teeth, undated
  - Molten Metal Endo File, undated
  - Reame Sterilizer, undated
  - Paper Disks, undated
  - Protractor, undated
  - Cloth Strips, undated
  - Antique Dental Instruments (15), undated
  - Plaques, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Saklad Nameplate, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Centennial Certificate, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Framed Faculty Photos (7), undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin R. Hoch Dental Toolkit with Tools, undated
  - NYU Banners (2), undated
  - Antique Dental Tools (20+) with Descriptions, undated
  - Glass plates (2), undated (Box Shared University Archives 011)
  - LP recordings (3): Century Club Dinner, NY Hilton, 1963-10-19 (Box Shared University Archives 079)
  - LP, 33-1/3: NYUCD Dental Violet, 1970 (Box Shared University Archives 079)
  - Dr. J. Van Chandler Dental Toolkit with Tools, undated
  - Saklad Nameplate, undated (Box 55)
  - Dental Toolkit and Tools, "Dr. Clarence Cohen", undated (Box 17)
  - NYU College of Dentistry building illustration, circa 1940s (Box Shared University Archives 010)
  - Dentistry Alumni Banner, undated (Box 53)
  - Film Reels (4): Class of 1952, class and fraternity activities, undated (Box 16)
  - Dental School scrapbook materials: reunion and class photographs, diplomas and diploma mock-ups, newspaper clippings, 1788-1965 (Box 44)
  - Framed dental tool, undated (Box 52)
  - Howard L. Ward Certificate of Honor - President of the College of Dentistry Alumni Assocation, 1974 (Box Shared University Archives 052, Folder 6)
- Series III: Student Records, 1866-1929; 4.5 Linear Feet
  - College of Dentistry Admission Cards, 1889-1907 (Box 18)
  - Student Report Cards, First - Third Year Class, 1913-1914 (Box 19)
  - Student Report Cards, 1914-1916 (Box 20)
  - Student Report Cards, 1926-1929 (Box 21)
  - J.L. Blass Notebooks, 1919,1929 (Box 22)
  - Student Lecture Notes in anatomy, anesthesia, surgery, hypnosis, oral surgery, physiology, undated (Box 23, Box 24)
  - Student Record Book, 1866-1906 (Box 54)
- Series IV. Accreditation Records, 1973-2003; 21.5 Linear Feet in 20 record cartons and 3 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials created through the course of a reaccreditation process that document various administrative and educational aspects of the College of Dentistry's programs. Materials include syllabi, information about the curriculum of the programs, reports outlining the programs' compliance with accreditation standards, and materials produced in preparation for accreditation site visits.
  - Predoctoral Curriculum, 1978-1989 (Box 25A, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 40, Box 41, Box 56)
  - Self-Study Reaccreditation Reports, 1980, 1996, 2003 (Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 57, Box 58)
  - Standards for Accreditation, 1989 (Box 35, Box 36, Box 59)
  - Syllabi, 1973-1975, 1989 (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 60, Box 61)
  - Grants for Health Professions Schools, 1980 (Box 41)
  - Manual for Accreditation Site Visit, 1980 (Box 41)
  - Task Force Report, 1976 (Box 42)
  - Manuals for Accreditation, 1989 (Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51)